Guide to the Humanities Council Records RG.9.5.1
New York University Archives
- Series III: Outside Programming, 1979-1989; 5.25 Linear Feet in 9 manuscript boxes, 1 half-manuscript box, and 3 folders in oversize flat boxes; 393 kilobytes in 69 computer files; 2 Quarter_Inch_Audio_Reel; 56 audiocassettes
  Shortly after its inception, the Humanities Council sought to partner with other institutions in the New York City metro area to support the humanities and humanities education beyond New York University. From 1979-1989, the Council participated in a joint humanities program with Rockefeller University (RU), wherein humanists from NYU led interdisciplinary humanities programming on the RU campus, and scientists from RU gave lectures for the NYU community. Rockefeller University specializes in scientific and medical education, and the Rockefeller/NYU Joint Program in the Humanities fit into the Council's broader aims to integrate humanities instruction into science, health, and professional programs. The Council also engaged with high school humanities instruction through two programs: the Rockefeller Foundation-funded High School Humanities Project, which ran from 1983 to 1988, and the Summer Institute, which was funded by the National Endowment for Humanities and ran from 1985 to 1989. The Council also liaised with the New York Council on the Humanities (NYCH) to plan conferences and lectures and to organize NYCH board meetings.
  Series III: Outside Programming (dated 1977-1989) contains records documenting the Humanities Council's efforts to promote interdisciplinary humanities studies among working professionals, other post-secondary educational institutions, and high schools. The documents in this series, particularly those related to the Summer Institute, show programming focused on the bicentennials of the U.S. Constitution and the French Revolution, which were topics of other Council programming created for an audience of working humanists and university students. The Council also worked with the New York Council on Humanities (NYCH) on programming targeted to working humanists, including conferences and lectures.
  This series has been arranged into three subseries. Files are arranged chronologically within subseries. The subseries arrangement of the records is as follows:
  Subseries III.A NYU and Rockefeller University Joint Program in the Humanities, 1979-1989
  Subseries III.B New York Council on Humanities, 1979-1992
  Subseries III.C High School Humanities Education, 1983-1989
  - Subseries III.A: NYU and Rockefeller University Joint Program in the Humanities, 1979-1989; 2 Linear Feet in 4 manuscript boxes and 2 folders in oversize flat boxes; 2 Quarter_Inch_Audio_Reel; 56 audiocassettes; 2.26 kilobytes in 18 computer files
    Subseries III.A New York University and Rockefeller University Joint Program in the Humanities (dated 1979-1989) documents the collaboration between NYU's Humanities Council and the administration of RU to foster interdisciplinary education for students in the humanities and sciences. The program is documented by Rockefeller/NYU Committee records, planning files, correspondence with potential participants, and publicity and marketing materials. This subseries also includes the National Endowment for the Humanities grant proposal and reports. Correspondence with participants, invitations, invitation lists, posters, and audio recordings document "Humanities at Rockefeller" programming, while "Scientists Speak About Science" is documented by planning files including event schedules, location bookings, and audio recordings.
    - Planning Files, 1979-1982 (Box 52, Folder 1-8, 22)
    - Rockefeller/NYU Committee, 1980-1989
      - Paper Records, 1980-1985 (Box 52, Folder 9-13)
      - Electronic Records, 1983-1989; RG_9-5-1_ER_88
    - Potential Speakers, 1982-1983
      - Paper Records, 1982-1983 (Box 52, Folder 14-17)
      - Electronic Records, 1982-1983; RG_9-5-1_ER_85
    - Publicity, 1980-1989 (Box 52, Folder 18-21)
    - Brochures, 1980-1992
      - Paper Records, 1980-1992 (Box 53, Folder 9-14)
      - Electronic Records, 1983-1984; RG_9-5-1_ER_84
    - National Endowment for the Humanities Proposal, 1980-1981 (Box 53, Folder 1-8)
    - Humanities Programming at Rockefeller University, 1980-1987
      - Inaugural Humanities Lecture: Isaac Bashevis Singer, 1980
        - Paper Records, 1980 (Box 53, Folder 15)
        - Poster, 1980 (Box 88, Folder 4)
      - Aileen Ward--"The Nature of Biographical Evidence", 1980 (Box 53, Folder 16)
      - Josephine Hendin--"Violence in Recent American Fiction", 1980 (Box 54, Folder 1)
      - Robert B. McKay--"Ethics and Jurisprudence", 1980 (Box 54, Folder 2)
      - Graham Hughes--"Modern Jurisprudence", 1980 (Box 54, Folder 3)
      - Denis Donoghue--"Aspects of Modern Literature", 1981 (Box 53, Folder 17)
      - A. Richard Turner--"Saint Francis and the Centaurs: Two Renaissance Landscapes in New York Collections", October 7, 1981 (Box 95, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0187)
      - William K. Everson--"Developments in the History of Cinema", 1981
        - Paper Records, 1981 (Box 54, Folder 4)
        - Audio Recording, December 1, 1981 (Box 90, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0034)
      - Edward Roesner--"The Restoration of Early Music", 1981 (Box 54, Folder 5)
      - Horst W. Janson--"The Image of the Human Soul in Art", 1981 (Box 54, Folder 6)
      - Donald Posner--"Erotic Imagery in Eighteenth-Century Art", 1981 (Box 54, Folder 8)
      - Carl Schorske--"Freud: The Psycho-archaeology of Cities", 1981 (Box 54, Folder 9)
      - Peter H. von Blankenhagen--"Process and Chance in Greek Art", 1981 (Box 54, Folder 10)
      - Concert Series, 1981 (Box 54, Folder 11)
      - David King at Rockefeller University, February 3, 1982 (Box 90, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0041)
      - Robert Rosenblum--"Picasso One Hundred Years Later", 1981
        - Paper Records, 1981 (Box 54, Folder 13)
        - Poster, 1981 (Box 88, Folder 4)
        - Audio Recording, October 27, 1981 (Box 90, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0055)
      - McGeorge Bundy--"Scientists, Decision-Makers, and H-Bombs: A Cautionary Tale, 1949-1982"
        - Paper Records, 1982 (Box 54, Folder 14)
        - Posters, 1982 (Box Shared University Archives 154, Folder 5, Box 88, Folder 4)
        - Audio Recording, March 8, 1982 (Box 90, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0037)
      - Louis Auchincloss--"A Novelist's Use of His Background and Environment", 1982
        - Paper Records, 1982 (Box 54, Folder 15)
        - Audio Recording, May 19, 1982 (Box 90, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0046)
      - Seminars in Humanities Posters, 1982-1983 (Box 88, Folder 4)
      - Sakhorov Symposium, 1981 (Box 54, Folder 7)
      - Jess Bessinger at Rockefeller University, November 3, 1982 (Box 90, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0053)
      - Ved Mehta--"Chachaji and the Writing of Literature", 1982
        - Paper Records, 1982 (Box 54, Folder 17)
        - Audio Recording, December 16, 1982 (Box 90, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0043)
      - An Evening with Louis Malle, 1983
        - Paper Records, 1983 (Box 54, Folder 18)
        - Audio Recording, March 3, 1983 (Box 90, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0045)
      - Jonathan Brown--"El Greco", May 1983 (Box 90, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0044)
      - Seminars in Humanities Promotional Materials, 1983-1984 (Box 54, Folder 16, 19)
      - Joseph Kerman--"Modern Views of Eighteenth-Century Music", 1983
        - Paper Records, 1983 (Box 54, Folder 20)
        - Electronic Records, 1983; RG_9-5-1_ER_80
        - Poster, 1983 (Box 88, Folder 4)
        - Audio Recording, October 21, 1983 (Box 96, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0212)
      - Eliot Friedson--"The Future of the Professions in the United States", November 2, 1983 (Box 96, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0213)
      - Brooks McNamara--"Medical Quackery on Stage: The History of the American Medicine Show", 1984
        - Audio Recording, February 2, 1984 (Box 95, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0179)
        - Electronic Records, 1984; RG_9-5-1_ER_77
      - Alfred Kazin--"The New York Writer and his Landscape", 1983-1984
        - Paper Records, 1983-1984 (Box 54, Folder 21)
        - Electronic Records, 1983-1984; RG_9-5-1_ER_76
        - Posters, 1983-1984 (Box 88, Folder 4)
      - Nicholas Wahl--"Socialism in France", March 7, 1984 (Box 95, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0183)
      - Lawrence Sager Lecture, May 2, 1984 (Box 95, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0189)
      - John E. Sexton--"Developments in Religion and the Law", October 3, 1984 (Box 95, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0193)
      - Thomas Bender--"The City and Intellectual Life", October 5, 1983 (Box 96, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0223)
      - Kirk Varnedoe--"'Primitivism' and Modern Art", 1984
        - Paper Records, 1984 (Box 54, Folder 23)
        - Poster, 1984 (Box 88, Folder 4)
      - Jacob T. Schwartz--"Artificial Intelligence: Possibility and Impact", October 11, 1984 (Box 96, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0214)
      - Marilynn Gelfman Karp--"The Civilizing and Resurrection of Objects or the Chemistry of Collecting", November 7, 1984 (Box 96, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0210)
      - Wassily Leontif--"The Technical Change and Its Economic and Social Implications", December 5, 1984 (Box 96, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0222)
      - Bernard Malamud--"The Long Writing Road", March 14, 1985 (Box 55, Folder 1)
      - Jacob T. Schwartz--"Developing Common Interest Between Neuroscience and Artificial Intelligence", October 2, 1985
        - Audio -- 1 of 2 (Box 95, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0170)
        - Audio -- 2 of 2 (Box 95, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0181)
      - Guy Walton--"Versailles", November 4, 1985 (Box 92, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0138)
      - Reyner Banham--"The Rhetoric of High Tech: European Developments in Style and Substance", 1985
        - Paper Records, 1985 (Box 55, Folder 3)
        - Audio Recordings, December 12, 1985
          - Audio -- 1 of 2 (Box 92, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0140)
          - Audio -- 2 of 2 (Box 92, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0141)
      - Deitrich von Bothmer--"Experiences of a Curator", February 5, 1986 (Box 92, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0143)
      - Rochelle Dreyfuss and David Leebron--"Employee Privacy in the Technological Age", March 3, 1986 (Box 91, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0146)
      - Frances Kamm--"Contemporary Ethical Thinking", April 2, 1986 (Box 94, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0148)
      - James W. Tuttleton--"City Literature: States of Mind", April 4, 1984 (Box 96, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0206)
      - Dr. Arthur Balin--"Thoughts on the Biological Mechanisms of Aging", April 10, 1986
        - Audio -- 1 of 2 (Box 92, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0150)
        - Audio -- 2 of 2 (Box 92, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0149)
      - Richard Sennett--"The Discovery of Narrative in the Social Sciences", May 5, 1986 (Box 90, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0156)
      - Philip Habib--"Myths and Reality in Foreign Affairs", May 19, 1986 (Box 90, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0159)
      - Cerami Lecture, December 11, 1986 (Box 93, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0099)
      - Eisler--"Leonardo and Anatomy", February 4, 1987 (Box 93, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0093)
      - Ralph Steinmen Seminar, February 12, 1987 (Box 93, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0096)
      - Movshon Lecture, March 3, 1987 (Box 93, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0094)
      - Finkel Seminar, March 12, 1987 (Box 93, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0095)
      - Heyns Seminar, April 5, 1987 (Box 93, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0090)
      - Emil Gotschlich Seminar, April 9, 1987 (Box 93, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0088)
    - Scientists Talk About Science at NYU, 1981-1985
      - Planning Files, 1981-1985 (Box 55, Folder 3-5)
      - Abraham Pais on Einstein, February 11, 1982 (Box 96, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0225)
      - Heinz Pagels--"Cosmology", December 9, 1982 (Box 95, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0172)
      - Fernando Nottebohm--"Permanence and Change in the Adult Brain", December 8, 1983
        - Audio -- 1 of 2 (Box 76, Quarter inch audio reel 9-5-1.0070)
        - Audio -- 2 of 2 (Box 76, Quarter inch audio reel 9-5-1.0071)
      - Purnell W. Choppin. How Does a Virus Cause Disease?", February 9, 1984 (Box 95, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0174)
      - Charles S. Peskin--"How Computers Can be Used to Design Prosthetic Heart Valves", April 12, 1984 (Box 96, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0207)
      - Nicola R. Khuri--"Unification in Physics: Maupertuis and Hamilton", November 8, 1984 (Box 96, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0200)
      - Rodney W. Nichols--"Science and Technology in the Third World", December 13, 1984 (Box 95, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0192)
      - Norton D. Zinder--"Genes, Scientists, and Others", February 14, 1985 (Box 95, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0180)
      - James E. Darnell--"Cell Evolution: How Did It Happen?", April 11, 1985 (Box 96, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0215, 9-5-1.0216)
        - Audio -- 1 of 2 (Box 96, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0215)
        - Audio -- 2 of 2 (Box 96, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0215)
      - Rifkin Lecture, October 10, 1985 (Box 92, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0133)
      - Allan R. Goldberg, November 14, 1985
        - Audio -- 1 of 2 (Box 92, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0135)
        - Audio -- 2 of 2 (Box 92, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0142)
      - Floyd Ratliff--"Illusions in Minds and Machines", February 13, 1986
        - Audio -- 1 of 2 (Box 92, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0144)
        - Audio -- 2 of 2 (Box 92, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0145)
      - E. D. G. Cohen--"The Quest for the Absolute Zero of Temperature", March 13, 1986 (Box 91, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0147)
    - Report on Joint Program in the Humanities, 1981-1982 (Box 54, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1983; RG_9-5-1_ER_86
    - Rockefeller Seminars in Humanities Planning Files, 1984-1986 (Box 54, Folder 22, Box 55, Folder 2)
  - Subseries III.B: New York Council on Humanities, 1979-1992; .5 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box; 4 kilobytes in 3 computer files
    Subseries III.B New York Council on Humanities (dated 1979-1992) includes materials documenting the Humanities Council's relationships with the New York Council on Humanities (NYCH). This subseries includes paper and electronic planning files for two conferences, one lecture series in collaboration, and planning files for an NYCH board meeting at NYU.
    - Work and Worklessness in New York State Conference, 1979 (Box 47, Folder 2)
    - NYCH Lecture Series, 1981-1989 (Box 47, Folder 3)
    - NYCH Board Meeting at NYU, 1983
      - Paper Records, 1983 (Box 47, Folder 4)
      - Electronic Records, 1983; RG_9-5-1_ER_82
    - The Anatomy of Hate: Saving Our Children Conference, 1992
      - Paper Records, 1992 (Box 47, Folder 5)
      - Electronic Records, 1992; RG_9-5-1_ER_89
  - Subseries III.C: High School Humanities Education, 1983-1989; 2.75 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes, 1 half-manuscript box, and 2 folders in oversize flat boxes; 31.6 kilobytes in 16 computer files
    Subseries III.C High School Humanities Education (dated 1983-1989) includes documents related to the Humanities Council's High School Humanities Project and the Summer Institute. The High School Humanities Project is represented by research files on high school education, correspondence with local high school administrators in New York City, and the Rockefeller Foundation grant reports and re-application. This subseries also includes paper and electronic budget files. Student newspapers and oral history projects from Seward High School provide examples of schools' High School Humanities Project activities. Most of the materials related to the Summer Institute are related to the "Age of Democratic Revolution" sessions. These include an National Endowment for the Humanities grant proposal for that specific project, semi-annual reports, and expense reports. There are also calls for proposals from the Council, curricular materials, posters, and planning files particular to the American Constitution Bicentennial and French Revolution Bicentennial sessions. This subseries also includes issues of the Summer Institute's "COLLABORATIVE" newsletter and a proposal for a session focused on Shakespeare.
    The Humanities Council was involved in two significant projects that focused on improving high school humanities education standards. The first was the High School Humanities Project, which ran from 1983 to 1988 and was funded with a grant from the Rockefeller Foundation. For this project, the Council facilitated resource sharing between New York City public high schools and activities such as student-led oral histories. In 1985, the Council began the Summer Institute, a series of seminars on NYU's campus for high school teachers during summer break. In 1987 and 1988, the Summer Institute sessions were built around the theme of "The Age of Democratic Revolution," with the 1987 session covering the bicentennial of the ratification of the United States Constitution and the 1988 session devoted to the bicentennial of the French Revolution. The National Endowment for the Humanities funded the "Age of Democratic Revolution" Summer Institute sessions.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Files related to student oral history projects, located in box 68, are restricted until 2063 to protect the privacy of interviewees.
    - High School Humanities Project, 1983-1988
      - Rockefeller Foundation Background Reports on Humanities Education, 1983 (Box 49, Folder 8, Box 50, Folder 1)
      - Seward High School Newspaper, 1983-1986 (Box 88, Folder 5)
      - High School Humanities Project Budget and Expenses, 1983-1986
        - Electronic Records, 1983-1984; RG_9-5-1_ER_79
        - Paper Records, 1985-1986 (Box 51, Folder 4-5)
      - High School Resource Sharing, 1983-1986 (Box 50, Folder 10)
      - Rockefeller Foundation Grant Report, 1984 (Box 51, Folder 1)
      - Rockefeller Foundation Grant Re-application, 1985 (Box 51, Folder 2-3)
      - High School Humanities Research File, 1984-1988 (Box 51, Folder 8)
      - NYC Public Schools Research File, 1986-1988 (Box 51, Folder 9)
      - RESTRICTED -- Oral Histories by High School Students, 1987-1988 (Box 68, Folder 1-2)
        This file is restricted for 75 years after the date it was created. It will be open for research in 2063.
    - Summer Institute, 1985-1989
      - National Endowment for the Humanities Grant Proposal--Summer Seminars for High School Teachers, 1985-1988 (Box 51, Folder 6-7)
      - Age of Democratic Revolution, 1986-1988
        - Age of Democratic Revolution National Endowment for the Humanities Proposal, 1986 (Box 47, Folder 7-8)
        - Call for Proposals, 1986 (Box 47, Folder 9)
        - Semi-Annual Grant Reports, 1987-1988 (Box 48, Folder 2-4)
        - Curricular Materials, 1987 (Box 47, Folder 10, Box 48, Folder 1)
        - American Constitution Bicentennial, 1987-1988 (Box 49, Folder 1-2)
        - French Revolution Bicentennial, 1988 (Box 49, Folder 3-4)
        - Posters, 1987-1988 (Box Shared University Archives 097, Folder 15)
        - Expenses, 1987-1988 (Box 48, Folder 5)
      - Shakespeare Proposal, 1988 (Box 49, Folder 5)
      - COLLABORATIVE Newsletter, 1989 (Box 49, Folder 6-7)
- Series IV: Projects, 1982-1996; 1 VHS; 82 audiocassettes; 747 kilobytes in 62 computer files; 15.25 Linear Feet in 29 manuscript boxes, 2 half-manuscript boxes, and 11 folders in oversize flat boxes
  Series VI: Projects (dated 1982-1996) documents the planning, promotion, and execution of large-scale Humanities Council programming projects. Project-specific grants funded most of these projects, and this series contains grant proposals, reports, and supporting documentation prepared for granting institutions. The book projects in this series, America in Theory and Greenwich Village: Culture and Counterculture, are documented with correspondence with contributors and publishers, drafts, publicity materials, and press clippings. The Greenwich Village, French Revolution, and Columbus Quincentenary project files include planning committee materials, topical research files, and information about related projects planned by other institutions. Files for all other projects besides America in Theory contain similar document types including correspondence with potential participants, event brochures and programs, invitations, lists of invitees, posters, and sometimes audio or video recordings of events.
  By the late 1980s, the Humanities Council pivoted to planning programming in the context of a multi-year series of events focused on a specific topic instead of organizing events by format, for example, a series of lectures on varied topics. Between roughly 1986 and 1996, the Council planned large projects on the themes of Greenwich Village history and culture (bulk 1988-1992), the bicentennial of the French Revolution (1986-1990), and the Quincentenary of Christopher Columbus's arrival in the Americas (1988-1983). The Council also planned programming related to the 100th birthday of Walt Whitman, the 150th birthday of Henry James, the 100th anniversary of cinema, and as a part of the Center for Atlanta History's "Exploring the Color Line" program. In 1988 America in Theory, an essay collection edited by Council director Leslie Berlowitz, was published.
  This series has been arranged into four subseries. Files are arranged chronologically within subseries. The subseries arrangement of the records is as follows:
  Subseries IV.A Greenwich Village, 1982-1992
  Subseries IV.B French Revolution Bicentennial, 1986-1990
  Subseries IV.C Christopher Columbus Quincentennial, 1988-1993
  Subseries IV.D Other Projects, 1986-1996
  - Subseries IV.A: Greenwich Village, 1982-1992; 3.5 Linear Feet in 7 manuscript boxes and 2 folders in oversize flat boxes; 15 audiocassettes; 22.4 kilobytes in 4 computer files
    In its early years, the Humanities Council sponsored projects and programming related to Greenwich Village. In the late 1980s, it began to plan cohesive programming to celebrate the Greenwich Village neighborhood. Leslie Berlowitz and Rick Beard edited Greenwich Village: Culture and Counterculture, a volume of essays on the history and culture of the area published by Rutgers University Press in 1993. Many of the essays in this volume had previously been published in Around the Square, 1830-1890: Essays on Life, Letters, and Architecture in Greenwich Village, published by NYU Press in 1982. In addition to publishing Greenwich Village: Culture and Counterculture, the Council also collaborated with the Museum of the City of New York on an exhibit titled "Within Bohemia's Borders" which opened in 1989, and planned lectures, readings, receptions, art exhibitions, and other programs that took place on NYU's campus and in Greenwich Village from 1989 through 1991. A National Endowment for the Humanities grant partly funded the Greenwich Village project.
    Subseries IV.A Greenwich Village (dated 1982-1992) contains files related to the book Greenwich Village: Culture and Counterculture, the "Within Bohemia's Borders" exhibition at the Museum of the City of New York (MCNY), and related programming and events developed and produced by the Council between 1989 and 1991. The book is documented by correspondence with Rutgers University Press, essay drafts interfiled with correspondence from contributing authors, press clippings, and planning files for a book launch event. The "Within Bohemia's Borders" exhibition at MCNY is represented with a poster, fliers, and correspondence between the Council and MCNY. Events planned as part of this project include lectures, film screenings, receptions, and readings, which are documented by correspondence with participants, invitations, posters, other promotional materials, and, in some cases, audio recordings of the event. Records of the Greenwich Village planning committee, the National Endowment for the Humanities grant proposal, press clippings, and publicity materials, including advertisements and press releases are also included and document the project as a whole.
    - Around the Square, 1982-1988 (Box 61, Folder 8)
    - Greenwich Village Planning Committee, 1988-1990 (Box 64, Folder 6)
    - Events, 1988-1992